A Guide to the Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Isle of Wight County (Va.) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926
The Library of Virginia
0007396693
.45 cu. ft. (1 box)
Isle of Wight County (Va.) Circuit Court
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
These items came to the Library of Virginia in shipments of court papers from Isle of Wight County.
Historical Information
Isle of Wight County was most likely named for the Isle of Wight off the south coast of England. It was first known as Warrosquyoake and was one of the eight shires established in 1634. The present name was given in 1637. Part of Nansemond County was added in 1769. Its area is 319 square miles, and the county seat is Isle of Wight.
The separate office of coroner appeared in Virginia about 1660. The judicial duty of the office is to hold inquisitions in cases when persons meet sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious death, or death without medical attendance. The coroner would summon a jury to assist him in determining cause of death. Prior to November 1877, the jurors numbered twelve. Between November 1877 and March 1926, the jurors numbered six. The jury viewed the body of the deceased and heard the testimony of witnesses. The coroner was required to write down witness testimony. After seeing and hearing the evidence, the jury delivered in writing to the coroner their conclusion concerning cause of death referred to as the inquisition. After March 1926, only the coroner determined cause of death. He could require physicians to assist him with determining cause of death. If a criminal act was determined to be the cause of death, the coroner was to deliver the guilty person to the sheriff and the coroners' inquests would be used as evidence in the criminal trial.
Scope and Content
Isle of Wight County (Va) Coroners' Inquisitions, 1784-1926, are investigations into the deaths of individuals who died by a sudden, violent, unnatural or suspicious manner, or died without medical attendance. Causes of death found in coroners' inquisitions include murder, infanticide, suicide, domestic violence, exposure to elements, drownings, train accidents, automobile accidents, and natural causes, or as commonly referred to in the 19th century, visitation by God. Documents commonly found in coroners' inquests include the inquisition, depositions, and summons. Criminal papers such as recognizance bonds can be found in coroner inquisitions. Information found in the inquisition include the name of the coroner, the names of the jurors, the name and age of the deceased if known, gender and race of the deceased, and when, how, and by what means the deceased came to his or her death. If the deceased was African American, the inquest would identify the deceased as a slave or free person if known. If the deceased was a slave, the inquest would include, if known, the name of the slaveowner and the slaveowner's residence. Information found in the depositions include the name of the deponent and his or her account of the circumstances that led to the death of the deceased. Slaves were occasionally deponents in coroner investigations.
Arrangement
Chronological by date coroner filed inquisition in the court.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Isle of Wight County (Va.) Circuit Court.
Subjects:
African Americans--History.; Coroners--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Death--Causes--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Free African Americans--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Infanticide--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Murder--Investigation--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Murder victims--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Slaveholders--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Slaves--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Suicide--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Women--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.
Geographical Names:
Isle of Wight County (Va.)--History.
Genre and Form Terms:
Death records--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Local government records--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.; Reports--Virginia--Isle of Wight County.
Selected Coroners' Inquisitions of Interest
- 1784 June 19, Death of Jane Womble:
  A pregnant Jane Womble and her four children (Samson, Richard, Loyd, and Cary) were murdered by her husband, Mathen Womble, who struck them about the head and neck with an axe.
- 1805 April 18, Death of Peter (slave):
  Peter, a slave owned by Thomas Smith, was stabbed in the stomach by Isham, a slave owned by Emanuel Wills, after a game of "five corns."
- 1816 January 3, Death of Natt Herring:
  Joe, a slave owned by Allen Fulgham, struck Herring in the neck with a stick, killing him instantly. Joe was found guilty of manslaughter in the criminal courts 5 February 1818 and sentenced to 39 lashes.
- 1827 September 13, Death of Unknown Infant:
  Female infant's death found to be from unknown causes, but the jury believed it probably the infant's death was caused by "some improper conduct" of its mother Airy, a slave owned by Rebecca Jones, who buried the infant in a "secret manner." The jury found it equally probably that the infant's death was caused by Airy's fall down some stairs a few days before the infant's birth.
- 1829 April 6, Death of Unknown Infant:
  Male infant died by the "inhumane conduct of its mother" Judea, a slave owned by John Womble, who wrapped the infant in cloths and placed it in a closed wooden box.
- 1829 November 2, Death of Caroline:
  The cause of death of Caroline, a former slave freed by the will of Joseph Cutchin, was unknown, the jury stated there was evidence before them that William Hall, with whom Caroline lived, tied and whipped Caroline and that thereafter she became ill and fell into a "stupor state" until her death. The jury found no marks of violence upon her body.
- 1831 March 7, Death of Unknown Infant:
  Infant died from neglect and a broken skull after its mother Letitia Briggs, a free person, placed the infant on the ground and covered it with pieces of wood.
- 1831 November 7, Death of Milly King and Unknown Infant:
  Milly King, a free person, was murdered by Wyat Johnson, another free Negro, who struck her in the head and neck with an ax. The blows caused King to fall from her chair onto her infant son, causing the infant's death.
- 1840 January 4, Death of James Turner:
  James Turner escaped from the Lunatic Hospital at Williamsburg, resisted arrest with a hatchet, and was shot by John S. Lattimere, who was attempting to arrest him.
- 1844 March 14, Death of Ruben (slave):
  Ruben, a slave owned by Jeremiah Delh, ran away from the possession of Henry Callcote with his hands tied with a rope. A month later his body was found floating in the waters of a mill pond with his hands still tied. Ruben was believed to have gone into the water of his own accord.
- 1844 April 2, Death of Dawson Teamer:
  Dawson Teamer, a Free Negro, assaulted and beat a Free Negro woman, Mary Rix, leaving on the land of Henry H. Womble. Upon hearing of the attack, Womble confronted Teamer and "threatened to correct him." Womble tied said Teamer with a rope who then escaped into a swamp. Womble pursued and was stabbed by Teamer several times. Womble, with the aid of Josiah Beal, gave Teamer 35 lashes and released him. Coroner believed Teamer died from the beating, which was ruled as self-defense.
- 1871 May, Death of Margaret Ann Elizabeth White:
  Cause of death unspecified, but the coroner believed her death by "violence supposed to have been caused at the hands of Lucas W. White and Ann P., his wife," parents of Margaret White. Inquisition includes testimony from neighbors who witnessed the child crying in the yard and unable to stand with the father, Lucas White, stating to her, "...if you don't hush you blaimed infurnal [sic] bitch I will come and stamp your blaimed infurnal brains out."
- 1892 April 4, Death of Agnes A. Williams:
  Death ruled to be from premature labor caused by ill treatment from her husband, James Williams, and from subsequent exposure in fleeing from husband.
- 1896 November 10, Death of Lucinta Holloway and Sallie Owens:
  Deaths ruled to be from unknown causes, but testimony from family members suggest that the women were poisoned by an unknown African American male, thought to go by the name Hill.
- 1905 November 22, Death of William Duck:
  Death ruled to be by "organic disease of the heart" includes a detailed description of the postmortem examination.
- 1906 May 17, Death of Chestine (alias Booty) Edwards:
  Cause of death of the child Chestine Edwards ruled to be from ill treatment by his father Henry Edwards. Testimony of witnesses claimed to have seen Edwards beating his son and leaving him to hang by his ankles.
- 1908 August 19, Death of Bennett Woodson:
  Cause of death ruled to be from a "lick" with some blunt instrument to the head by some unknown person. Inquisition includes lengthy testimony from witnesses, including a detailed description of the postmortem examination.